this is a question in terms
of the practice of
non-resistance or
peacefulness so in terms of practicing
peaceful equanimous
non-resistance could this not in fact be
enabling harm for example if one tolerates
harm for example if one tolerates
abuse or Injustice without
resistance does this not just allow and
even encourage harmful Behavior to
continue unchecked I can understand that violence
unchecked I can understand that violence
is wrong to a degree but maybe it is
Justified if it is used to destroy
something that causes harm to oneself
and others so
isn't well depends what your priorities
are if you want to live in a better
world that's still fundamentally
subjected to destruction as
samsara then yes there is a line there
that you
can that you can
cross and defend
protect make the society better through
fighting Injustice and all of that but
that's still a worldly
Affair but if you want to practice to be
free from zumara then he has to be taken
in a Universal
sense without exception so anything
worldly including good things in the
world are
a an equal
trap and they have to also be
abandoned so that's why the precepts are
not really
negotiable cuz see you're still you will
not be able to not act out of attachment
gratuitously assume possessions craving
desire and passion
when you are fighting the Injustice when
you're defending you know the the the
the righteous ownership you won't be
able so you have a choice you could be
worldly righteous
person but that means you will
disqualify yourself from practicing D
rightly if that's the choice you make no
I will defend because it's important to
me okay that means abandoning the
ownership that's the root of suffering
in the wholesome s it's not important to
you because they're mutually exclusive
so you can't have fighting and
defending without implicit possession
ownership which is all kind of a
mistaken already that's mistaken sets of
identity that you are perpetuating
through such
acts you are attached you can't you
cannot not be you don't start neutral as
I as I often say
so so yes exactly I mean freedom from
samsara means freedom from the world
just or injust World means abandoning it
all to to its own um means and devices
it's not your
problem or if you could choose to make
it your problem but even then you choose
so because you have a desire to do
so so it's never justifiable either way
Nothing free freedom from from from
samsara and complete arship is not
written in the sky as a must for
everyone uh fighting for Injustice
fighting against Injustice in the world
it's not justifiable idea whatever you
choose to do is because you chose to do
so so if you want to practice foran ship
it's on the basis of you choosing to do
so if you want to fight for the
betterment of the world it's again
because you have a desire that you
follow and you make choices
accordingly so if you recognize that
it's up to you to decide that whatever
you choose the weight of that will be on
you so see if you choose to practice for
Samara to freedom from samsara
the weight of abandoning the world and
not protecting those in need of
protection and stuff that will be on
you but if you choose to fight for those
and abandon your path of Liberation
against samsara well that weight of that
will be on
you so it's up to you to decide really
what you want and then take
responsibility for it and do
it and you can and but you can't can't
do it both if you're honest you will
recognize that these choices are
mutually exclusive you can't do it you
can't have it all so which is more
important to you a better world
now but then you
know the uncertain future cuz you know
you might well fix all the world
problems and you'll die and what you
think the world will stay perfect
Forever After GED diversion delusion of
other individuals will not Prevail as it
always does so you recognize it's an
immediate immediately visible thing I
can do that can immediately verify my
efforts but it's relatively futile
overall from a greater scheme of things
it's it's not it's not going to make a
difference like things you know change
yeah why am I practice
samsara well it's not immediately
verifiable it might take years before
you get even any insight into freedom
from suffering and so on
but if you succeed well it's the
ultimate impact so there is some risk
impact so there is some risk
involved but then there is a greater
reward the other one has less risk
involved because you can immediately
judge your efforts of success whe the
Injustice is disappearing and so on but
the the reward is lesser it's lesser
it's not not as lasting
either so it's really not um people pose
this question as if like you know what
what's the Buddhist perspective there's
no Buddhist perspective on social issues
as far as the Buddhist perspective goes
is keep the five precepts for those
concerned in the world that don't want
to abandon the world the Buddha only
thought suffering and freedom from it
that's the Buddhist
perspective so if that's not what you're
interested in then keep the five
precepts and be a good man and look
after your family and yeah try not to
harm others
but yeah that's the best advice that's
that's the the extent of the advice you
can give for worldly Affairs doesn't
matter yeah best advice so the Buddhist
perspective is free yourself from
suffering and for that yeah of course
it's better but if you choose not to do
it then the Buddhist perspective does
not apply to you but the reason I bring
this up is because that question often
comes from somebody who kind of implies
both I am practicing ultimately but look
all of this so surely we can find a
common ground here I can kill if it's
you know a bad person that would defend
others and stuff you
can but that disqualifies you pretty
severely from any successful practice of
the
dhama or say like you know with lying oh
sometimes it's good to lie because you
know you might save a life and stuff
well there are many factors you can
start considering but again is it is it
a worldly
concern is it for the betterment of the
of the the world and stuff you save
lives but again what will those lives be
useful proliferation of sensuality and
stuff what if those lives now commit
even greater harm in the future people
make different choices so now that's on
you isn't it the good
deed so it's like you're interfering
you're engaging in worldly Affairs which
means they're going to be consequences
good or bad one way or the other you
will remain bound to it that's the
point if that's your choice fine but
don't entertain the idea that you can do
both and not or not be bound to it by
doing worldly things and not be bound to
because you are Buddhist and you imagine
Detachment every now yeah exactly no no
that's not so I think most of the work
not so I think most of the work
basically just comes from developing
this self- honesty and really
recognizing where that hard choice
is and then seeing like cuz you know
like sometimes you have people that
think they can't abandon the worldly
Affairs and practice rightly because
this Choice was not clear to them once
the choice becomes clear they realize
actually they have it in them to do
it and then you also have people that
think they're doing it but they're doing
it because the choice is not clear once
the choice becomes clear they realize
they can't do it they can't give up the
world as long as the the
choice is clear that's the that's the
important part yeah you know then you
know that you're not well then you're
not fooling yourself not yeah cuz again
yeah it's the clarity the absence of the
clarity thinking that you can do both
that's why the person that could
actually is able to give up the world
and do it that's why they're not doing
it because they're not they haven't been
taught they haven't learned they hasn't
sun in that no no I need to recognize
that I can't do both and because of that
they're not really doing it rightly CU
just they think they can have a bit of
this and a bit of
that and the one that's thinking they're
really practicing rightly
on the basis of ignoring that very
Clarity of that choice that needs to be
made then once they recognize that then
they'll realize oh I don't want to do
this if if this is required if this
choice is required for the beginning of
the practice then I don't want to do it
so the only reason they were doing it is
because they were not doing it but it's
it's a it's a clear cut between world
you know every every like all those
instructions in the sutas about given to
the monks uh you know the
anapanasati or saatana or just general
Jan instruction or those Reflections
when they go into the CTI and you the C
is empty and then they reflect on that
and how nothing belongs to them and
nobody and they don't belong to anybody
and it all kind of begins with that
basic mindfulness which as a
prerequisite the basic mindfulness as a
prerequisite has
overcoming all the joys and concerns in
regard to the world no
exception completely
withdrawn from it then you can
start the right
cultivations and uh and I think today
that whole mess between like oh you know
you can do both and Buddhist perspective
on this and that and the Buddha taught
lay people how to practice same like he
did monks which he never did um and it's
like that that all exists just because
well this hasn't been stated hard enough
put teach is compassion that's whatever
compassion whatever comp do I de as the
compassion that is practicing bum yeah
so then you could see like how naturally
then you know you can't really blame
people yeah because naturally then leads
to okay so what's then the Buddhist
perspective on this issue what do you do
in this issue all completely worldly
issues and and usually it kind of
revolves on like basically some worldly
solution or the other yeah remember the
person once asked ask somebody
else not me but I was there and he was
asking like
oh what does the Buddhism offer what
does the Buddhism do to all the starving
children in Southeast Asia it was it was
maybe in the news or something there was
some big starvation children dying not
enough food not enough means what is
like what is you know you being a monk
what does what does what does Buddhism
do for that and this person obviously I
don't know maybe they got caught with
that question they just started
answering but you realize hold on like
that's a
completely completely wrong question
it's like would you go to a random bus
driver and ask them what does your bus
driving do to Starving Children
Indonesia you wouldn't it wouldn't it
wouldn't even occur to you to bring the
two together but
somehow your life of a
your life of a
monk has to be doing something for
that so it was like you don't ask any
other profession because it's not your
problem but somehow it's expected that
Buddhism must involve itself in this and
must offer a
perspective but the point is ironically
Buddhism does a lot
more if they were actually following the
Buddhist principles they would not have
had so many
children they would have not engaged in
sexual intercourse they would have
practice restraint there would be no
starving children but it's because people were
children but it's because people were
giving into sensuality men and women
alike not thinking through that there is
not enough means for them to survive and
producing children left and right
now there is not enough food to Fe and
children are dying it's horrible but it
could have been prevented if they follow
the Buddhist principle if they follow
what the monk
says keep the precepts and if you
proliferate if you have if you have
children you have to do it wisely With a
Purpose with a recognition with
perspective not just well we'll deal
with it yeah so it's like it does a lot but
it yeah so it's like it does a lot but
you have to follow it
but this expectation that the Buddhist
teaching in the practice has to be
appeasing the worldly Affairs it's not
supposed to me being a monkey is not
supposed to help Starving Children it's
supposed to free me from
samsara hopefully enough with enough
understanding so I can teach to others
who want to do that profession who want
to choose the path of leaving the world
and freeing themselves from some s
that's it it's a very limited
application Taste of salt the sea has
only one taste which is a taste of salt
as they would have said he's teaching
has only one taste which is freedom from
suffering that's it oh but how does your
freedom from suffering help my
architectural degree your practice for
freedom from suffering it's a absolutely
irrational question yet it's often asked in this
question yet it's often asked in this
Buddhist Circle because the whole
perversion of the values and blurring
the lines whereby now people think no no
no you must you being a must also be
helping this and helping
that there is that view
that a human being has responsibility to
help others yes
yeah that's a worldly view yeah yeah
what but
why there is as I said your duty to help
others the only responsibility that you
have is basically to recognize
that you are the one responsible for
your choices and desires there is no
external factor that can justify that
it's not saying that it's bad to help
others it's just recognizing that it's a
direction that
requires concern passion attachment
involvement but that that if you want to
help others what would be the best thing
to do exactly and is there a path that
helps others in a greater way there is
no attachment from your side exactly and
that's that's the kind of the whole
recognition of the bigger picture animal
realm human realm it's just endless
endless recurring repetition of same
stuff 100 years ago 500 years ago same
worries same anxieties same
desires same battle same engagement same
Injustice same Justice same fixing same
messing up and as Buddha said it's enough monks
up and as Buddha said it's enough monks
for revulsion it's enough for dispassion
recognizing that it's more than enough
to inspire you towards complete this
passion towards the whole thing you just
refuse to look at it so the practice is
really just keeping it in front of your
eyes the obvious until this passion will
be the natural outcome so the reason
people are not dispassionate is they
don't keep this in front of their eyes
sufficiently enough that they don't let
it sink in because it's
unpleasant initially it's
unpleasant it's like yeah any hope you
know any desire you
have at least at that point in the
beginning is bound with that world and
now it just feels like oh all of that is
like oh none of that is worth it so it
is it is quite a an
impactful but you would come down within
that and then you would recognize that
well whether you upset on account of it
or not that is factually the truth that
that you can observe even now even in
your limited experience in this life you
could already see yeah but how many
times already no multiply that
already no multiply that
by thousandfold yeah and then
nightm yeah so even if you do good and
help can you guarantee that things won't
change again and won't even get worse no
and you know it will so one way or the
other whatever you choose to do so you
do so because you just want to fulfill
your desire to do it that's it that is
like kind of the
the the conviction you have to be
serving whether you want it or not
that's the extent that that is the
extent of your engagement of your
capacity to engage is on the basis of
your desire good desire bad desire still
you're pressured you're engaged when
that's fulfilled you can't care even if
you want
to you will move on your mind will move
on when the changes when the feeling
changes it's done
so yes you can often you know some
people are more compassionate than
others some people more often revolve
around these things and nobody says
that's bad but he has he has its expired
date limited limited very limited
exactly so that's why the basic practice
of mindfulness starts by overcoming
entirety the entirety of concerns choice
in regard to anything that comes from
the world